the trend is your friend until it ends
but eventually every trend has to come
to an end the market will reverse at
some point and if you are buying in an
uptrend and it flips on you you're going
to take a loss but what if we could see
when these reversals were likely to take
place so that rather than taking losses
we could take advantage of the new
direction of the market and actually
profit from reversals well that's what
I'm going to show you in this video I'm
going to teach you how to identify
reversals how to confirm reversals so
you lose less and win more and how to
take advantage of the new direction that
the market makes and let's not waste any
time let's get straight to the learning
so when we have a clear Trend in a
market it's great we can just
continually buy each low if the market
is in an uptrend and we can look to
profit from the movement up but
eventually we may go for a buy and then
the market will flip on us this trend is
not going to last forever and the market
will eventually reverse which means if
you are buying in this uptrend
eventually you're going to lose now
there is actually a way that we can
identify when the market is reversing
but we can't just guess at when the
reversal is going to take place we can't
just sell every high in the market
because it can just continue moving
higher one of the worst things people do
is what we call catch a falling knife
where they think okay the Market's been
going up or down for so long that it has
to reverse now so I'll buy right now or
I'll sell because it has to turn around
it's been going down or up for too long
the market can stay irrational longer
than you can stay solvent meaning the
market can do whatever the market wants
to do even if it seems like it logically
has to turn around that doesn't mean it
will so so we cannot catch falling
knives we cannot sell tops randomly we
cannot buy lows we have to confirm
reversals and I'll show you how to do
that right now the absolute first thing
we need when looking for reversals is
context we need to see a reason for the
market to reverse so if we take a look
at the current downtrend that's
happening in this market how would we
know when this is going to turn around
well some amateur Traders would look and
think it's been going down for so long
it has to go back up so I'll buy it now
this is obviously a terrible idea AA
because we don't know when this Market
is going to reverse you are blindly
guessing and that's not going to be a
good way to trade long term even if it
pays you off once or twice so to get
context what we want to do is look to
the left if we take a look at some of
the older price action and the previous
movements formed in the market we can
build context behind where reversals
might take place now the two ways that I
like to look for context are going to be
through supply and demand and key levels
so supply and demand refers to supply
and demand zones a demand zone is a
consolidation area before a large up
move we then use this consolidation and
when the market pulls back to this level
we buy once again and a supply zone is
the opposite it's consolidation before a
down move when the market pulls back
that becomes a high probability selling
point I've got a full video on supply
and demand if you don't understand the
concepts at all there's a card somewhere
in the corner of the video now the
second thing is key levels so key levels
are basically horizontal lines that we
draw on the chart and they would be
situated at the 0000 the 250 the 500 and
the 750 levels now these are basically
seen as institutional price levels that
larger players take profits at or get
into positions at it's nice rounded off
numbers we see reversals take place
around these levels so by looking at
this chart with the new concepts of
supply and demand and key levels we can
see that just down here there's a demand
zone so there's a consolidation before a
large up move now this consolidation
candle with the Wicks either the side is
going to be what we use as our demand so
we can mark that candle from the high to
the low and this becomes our demand
range when the market falls into this
region that would be a high probability
area to start seeing a reversal here we
can see that within that we have the
1.21 key level so the 0000 key level
that's a very rounded off number this is
another point of which Market reversals
take place so now we've got two reasons
for reversal we've got the key level
we've got the demand and we can see
above that we don't really have anything
now you might be asking isn't this a
demand Zone here this consolidation
before the large up move yes it is but
the market has come back and retested it
already as you can see once the demand
Zone has been retested it is no longer
of use to us this one has not been so
this is still in focus with this new
context we can see that basically
between that demand in this region here
there is no reason for reversal there's
no demand zones there's no core key
levels lining up with any demand zones
there's pretty much no reason for us to
reverse until we reach this demand so
this range here is pretty much an open
range that we could trade through now
when we do get towards that 1.21 and
that demand Zone this is where reversals
are highly likely to take place okay
we've got a high probability region with
a high probability key level this is
where the reversal would take place from
so rather than going for the opportunity
to catch a falling knife and buying here
simply because the market is moving down
you've now got two opportunities first
of all you can actually find opportunity
in the selling movement so you can look
for trades on Lower time frames to sell
down through this open range because we
know there's no reason to reverse in
here and then second of all when we
reach this area we can start looking for
those reversals so that we can profit
from the reversal back to the upside
okay and I'll show you how to do that in
just one minute but let's take a look at
how the market plays out you will see we
come down comfortably trading into this
area so that is Step number one context
once we have context behind why a
reversal might take place that provides
us with the first thing we need to see
we now have a high probability area we
are not so much just buying for the sake
of buying or catching a falling knife
but there's something else we need to
talk about because okay the market could
reverse from this point but then we
could say it could also reverse from
this point down here why would it not do
that that's entirely true and that can
happen which means if you buy into the
market here you can still lose cuz maybe
the market wants to reverse from a lower
Point instead or maybe it just wants to
continue selling for the longer term so
in order to avoid piling on buys at
every single area that the market could
reverse from we can now introduce a
concept that I call the standard
confirmation to identify which way the
market is going we want to view the
price structure highs and lows so a
market that's continually forming higher
highs and higher lows like this one here
is in an uptrend and we should only look
to buy a market that is forming lower
lows and lower highs is in a downtrend
and we should only be looking to sell
through this trend now to avoid catching
a falling knife we never want to buy in
a downtrend we never want to sell in an
uptrend we need to make sure that the
market is in agreement with us before we
start taking buys or sells so as
discussed a market that's forming higher
highs and higher lows like this is an
uptrending Market but what we can
actually do is plot these higher lows
and once the market breaks one of these
higher lows that would actually drive us
into a lower low okay so like this now
what do we know from that downtrending
example we just showed when we see lower
lows we expect that to be followed by
new lower highs and then new lower lows
and the market shifts into a downtrend
so this entire piece of price action
just here is what I call that standard
confirmation it's a very repeatable
pattern we're going to see it a lot of
times in the market and what it is that
we're looking for is simply a shift from
an uptrend into a downtrend by
identifying that break of structure at
the reversal point where the higher lows
shift into lower lows and then we are
looking to sell the lower high just here
so what we're seeing now is a full-on
reversal and the structure agrees with
us which is why we want to see this
before we get into trades now the same
is exactly true for a downtrend when a
downtrend starts breaking from lower
lows and lower highs into a higher high
then we can use that next leg of
structure to try and buy a higher low so
by bringing the structural confirmation
in we're no longer just relying on the
context from the higher time frame zones
but we can actually use the structure
that we see on the lower time frames
inside of those points of interest to
get the highest probability reversals so
now let's go back to the example we were
looking at before and I'll show you how
to put this into action all right so
we're back to this example as you can
see we've got our context we've got
demand we've got a key level this is
where a reversal is likely to take place
if anywhere so to bring in the standard
confirmation and make this trade
incredibly safe and high probability
what we want to see is basically this
pattern taking place out of this Zone
and if we see the structural shift here
to higher highs we will use the higher
low here as our buy Point that's where
we want to buy from okay now generally
when we're enacting this standard
confirmation we're going to go to a
slightly lower time frame because we
want to see a more scaled in view of the
price action so for this example I would
go down from the daily to the 4our and
by the way guys this works on absolutely
any time frame doesn't have to be the
daily in 4 Hour it could be the 10
minutes and 1 minute if you wanted it to
be so now on the 4our time frame what do
we want to see well we want to see the
market retest this 1.21 key level and we
also want to see some structural shifts
taking place in the market like this
where we will then look to buy this low
so let's allow this Market to play
forward and see if we get a retest of
that key
level so as you can see we've now came
into that key level area we've started
to see a little reversal down here but
it wouldn't be safe to buy just here now
you can make a career out of buying
inside of zones without using this
confirmation but your win rates will be
low and I want to teach you guys to be
accurate Traders so what can we see in
this market then we've got a lower low
lower high we've got a lower low lower
high lower low lower high lower low
lower high lower low okay so from a
structural point of view this is going
to be the point that we want to see
broken this is the lower high that would
change the trend so if the market is now
able to push up we would then identify a
demand Zone to buy from place our orders
and then see how the market plays out so
here we have a little formation we
haven't broken structure just yet
there's the break that's what we want to
see now we want to identify demand okay
so for me I would use this candle down
here I would cover the entire we but
basically we're looking to use this
consolidation before the large up move
and I always want to use the last candle
before the impulse now for me the last
candle before the impulse in this
instance is going to be this small
candle here but I always want to clear
the lows so I'm going to actually use
this larger range from the high of that
candle down to the very low of this Wick
so now that we've had that standard
confirmation we've had the break of
structure we have this demand Zone open
what we would do is place our orders
here so we' place our order on the
demand Zone our stop loss is going to go
beneath the low and then our targets are
going to go upwards to well wherever we
wanted to Target so for this example
let's actually take the market all the
way back up to these highs in the trend
here we're seeing if we can get a
fullblown reversal in the market here so
we might as well be ambitious with our
targets now all we would need to do is
allow the market to play out with orders
placed so that would be a buy limit
providing the market Taps Us in we
should then be on for a profitable move
because we have the trade confirmed so
there we go we got our retest of the
demand Zone at this point just here now
we will see how the market plays out as
you can see from the daily perspective
we've now shifted entirely into a new
trend okay so on our way through towards
the target you can see the market is now
forming higher highs and higher lows
consecutively so rather than forming
lower low lower high price action like
we were previously we got that
structural shift and the market has
completely changed Direction into an
uptrend now this uptrend in itself would
provide new opportunities for you to buy
throughout upon the formation of each
new low but catching the reversal gives
you the biggest trade it's going to give
you the highest risk reward and the
largest amount of Pips that you can
actually profit from because you're
catching the movement at the very bottom
but you're not gambling into it you're
actually waiting for the structural
shift to agree with you to tell you the
trend is now bullish that's exactly what
we did and the market has played through
into our analysis very very nicely so
there you go a solid example where the
market shifted from lows into highs and
provided us with a safe confirmed
reversal that we could trade out of now
leading this into a live example as of
right now if we were looking at this
Market where would be the point where we
would expect a reversal to take place
next so obviously at the moment the
market is bullish it's just trending up
there's no real reason for us to reverse
if we were going to look for a reversal
where would it be from well it would be
from this Supply Zone at the top of the
trending move why is that because there
is no other Supply Zone that hasn't yet
being retested so the market can easily
creep up towards this point and then
provide reversal opportunity from there
so now you can see there was some
trickier price action some Trends inside
of the larger Trend that we could have
taken advantage of on the lower time
frames but now that we've met this
Supply I want to show you the 4-Hour
time frame as to where we are right now
if you take a look at how the market is
moving right now we can see the market
structure has shifted up here we've gone
into higher high higher low higher high
and then the market came down and broke
that structural low putting us now into
what could be the start of a downtrend
so something I want you to follow in the
future because we can't put it in this
video because this is real time is what
does the market do next I'd be looking
at this kind of region here for a
reversal in price with also the
potential that the market could get up
to this point and then reverse so just a
little live one for you keep an eye on
this market and see what happens in
terms of reversals from this point here
or this point here don't guess your way
into trades and get caught catching
falling knives make sure every trade
you're looking for has context and if
we've got good context then make sure
you wait for that confirmation so you
can have the highest probability highest
odds of success and now the best video
to watch next is this one which
elaborates more on Market structure so
go and check that out alternatively
there's a free course in the description
I hope you enjoyed the video thanks for
watching I'll see you in the next one